# 大家好 我們去摘點那個螃蟹來吃
Hi everyone! We're gonna pick some crabs.
# 哦 不是
Ah, no!
# 摘萢子 說錯了
Pick berries. I mixed them up.
# 抓螃蟹 摘萢子
Catch the crabs, pick the berries.
# 這個路邊上的這個萢子 很好吃的哦
The berries on the, well, on the road, are really tasty, you know.
# 你看這些農村 農村的好多地方的萢子
Look! These are the berries, these are the berries which grow in many places in the villages.
# 都沒人摘來吃
But nobody picks them.
# 太浪費啦
What a waste!
# 我來消滅它們
Let me tackle them.
# 這種萢子就熟透啦 這種
This kind of berries are fully ripe, this one.
# 烏黑發亮
It's shinning dark.
# 啊~
Ah~
# 你看 這路邊上
Look! The peaches are everywhere,
# 到處都是桃子
on the side of the path.
# 好多啊 一樹都是
A lot! All over the tree
# 沒熟 等熟了時候
They're still green. I'll ask my buddy to come with me,
# 我叫兄弟過來一起
when they become ripe.
# 兄弟很喜歡吃桃子的哦
My buddy loves peaches, you know.
# 你看 有好多這個 萢子
Look! Here are a lot of this kind of, berries.
# 又好又紅
Big and red
# 誒呀
Eya!
# 這樣吃才過癮
This is the best way to enjoy the berries.
# 上次我們吃把它串起來吃
We skewed them up last time.
# 這樣子走
But I think make,
# 走 走那個形式不好啊
make, making too much gimmick is not my style.
# 直接摘來吃就好了
I prefer simply picking it and putting it into my mouth.
# 串來 串起來還不是一樣吃
Skew, skewing them up makes no difference.
# 啊 這個
Ah! This is...
# 誒 壞的
Eh? It's rotten.
# 太熟了
It's too ripe.
# 你看這個
Have a look at this one.
# 烏黑發亮
It's shiny dark!
# 用嘴巴一吸
Suck it with the mouth,
# 就
then,
# 就吃掉啦
then it's swallowed.
# 你看
Look!
# 這一些
These are...
# 這個壞的
This is rotten.
# 好多啦
There are too many.
# 嗯 剛好看到一個臭屁蟲
Um! I just saw a stink bug.
# 從這裡走過 有點臭 臭屁蟲的味道
It just passed by. So this one is a bit stinky, with the smell of a stink bug.
# 不要啦
Pass!
# 哇 這上面好多啊
Wa! There are a lot up there!
# 甚麼都不搞那麼快 哎呀
There's nothing urgent. Aya!
# 先吃飽再行動
Let's fill up our stomachs first.
# 這裡的全都壞的
These here are all rotten.
# 嗯
Um!
# 不好吃
No good.
# 好酸吶
It's so sour.
# 這裡面的品種不一樣
The species here is different.
# 好啦 不要啦
Alright! That's it!
# 留給後面的人來摘
I leave them to those after us.
# 你看
Look!
# 這一個
This is,
# 這一個是
this is a,
# 萢子王一樣的 那麼大
it's like a Berry King. It's so big!
# 啊
Ah!
# 可以
Not bad!
# 你看 兄弟家的牛哦
Look! These are my buddy's cattle.
# 小牛
Cowy!
# 還認不認識我
Can you still recognize me?
# 肚子那麼大 它的肚子
It has a big belly, its belly.
# 吃得太飽了
It has eaten too much.
# 你看 它理都不理我
Look! It ignores me completely,
# 理都不理我
ignores me completely.
# 下次我叫兄弟
Next time, I'll ask my buddy,
# 把你賣給我
to sell you to me.
# 看你還敢不敢
I'll see if you would behave!
# 我要把你養大
I'm gonna bring you up.
# 養大之後來呀 把你 吃你的肉
When you grow up, I'll, I'll put your beef onto my dish.
# 哇 你看 這個河水
Wa! Look! The water in this river,
# 好乾淨的哦
is so clean, you know.
# 你看 搬一下這裡 看有沒有
Look! I'll lift the rock and see if there are any,
# 螃蟹
crabs.
# 一個都沒有
Not even one!
# 你看 這個
Look! This rock,
# 這個石頭應該是有的
I think there's something under this rock.
# 哇 有一個
Wa! A crab!
# 看一下 那麼大的螃蟹
Look! What a big crab!
# 你看 那麼兇悍
Look! It's so aggressive!
# 有一兩重哦
It weighs about 50 grams.
# 你看這個 這個石頭應該是 這個石頭應該
Look! This, this rock should be, this rock must be...
# 誒 毛剛剛看到啦 啊 這裡這裡
Eh? I just saw it. Ah! Here, here!
# 一個
A crab
# 又找了一個
So one more.
# 那些石頭上壓著肯定有
Whenever there's a rock, there are always crabs underneath.
# 好像 有的樣子哦 (註︰這句很難又準確又自然的翻譯，有想過"It seems that here are crabs"，但太勉強了)
I would be surprised if there are no crabs here.
# 沒有
Really no
# 你看 這不是在勾引我嗎？
Look! Isn't it seducing me?
# 就長在河邊
It just grows on the riverside,
# 長得又大
and it's big,
# 又紅
and red.
# 哇
Wa!
# 嗯 好吃
Um! Tasty!
# 長到河邊來啦
They're growing onto the riverside.
# 你看 這個石頭下面應該有
Look! There should be, should be a crab,
# 應該會有一個
under this rock.
# 哎呀 看到沒有
Aya! Can you see it?
# 它在這裡
It's here.
# 還想著走
It still wants to run away.
# 夠大吧
Big, isn't it?
# 三個啦
Three now
# 你看 這個水潭好深啊 要從這裡鑽過來
Look! This pond is really deep. So we have to detour along this side.
# 鑽的過去嗎
Is it really possible?
# 這麼大的石頭 (註︰沒有原字幕)
What a big rock!
# 站得高望得遠 (註︰Climb high see wide，是香港一所中學的校訓，中文是「登高見博」XD)
Climb high, see wide
# 休息一下
Take a rest!
# 抓子半天抓了一隻
We've been here for the whole afternoon, only to have caught just three.
# 前面就很多啦
There are a lot in front of us.
# 哇 這裡有一個
Wa! Here's one!
# 這裡
Here!
# 誒 這裡還有一個
Eh? Here's another one!
# 它們小兩口
They're a young couple.
# 這是公的 這個是母的
This is male, and this is female.
# 不知道它們在乾嘛
I wonder what they're doing.
# 兩個把你抓起來
I'll capture both of you.
# 兩個人躲在一個屋子里面
They were hiding themselves from the world, under the same roof.
# 這裡有一個
Here's one.
# 誒 跑了嗎
Ey? It ran away?
# 小魚
A small fish
# 誒呦 那麼小就夾人的
Eyo! It pinches though it's so small.
# 嗯 這裡有一個
Um! Here's one.
# 嘿
Hey!
# 你看
Look!
# 螃蟹兒子 那麼小
Crab Jr., it's so small.
# 怕不怕我
Are you scared of me?
# 兩個螃蟹
Two crabs,
# 不是兩個螃蟹 兩個鉗子
I mean to pincers, not two crabs.
# 張開想夾我 是不是
Both are open. It wants to pinch me, right?
# 你還嫩了一點 還小
You're still too green. You're still small.
# 哎呀算了 把你放走了那麼小
Aya! Alright! I let you go. You're so small.
# 都不夠我一口吃掉
You're too small even for a single bite.
# 你自由啦
You're free now!
# 長大一點
Be a big crab!
# 可以叫你老爸老父媽出來
You can ask your dad and your mom to come.
# 你看
Look!
# 這個石頭下面不知道有沒有
Let's see if there are any crabs under this rock.
# 誒 有一隻
Eh! One!
# 現在的螃蟹都那麼大啦
The crabs are all that big now.
# 小的我都看到好幾個 好小
I've seen a couple of small ones. They're really small.
# 差不多夠了
It's almost enough.
# 這裡藏了
Here are...
# 好多這些田螺 就這種小的
Here are a lot of this kind of river snails. They're this kind of very small ones,
# 小石螺
small snails.
# 我們這個叫山坑螺 (註︰沒有原字幕)
They're called "stream snails" here.
# 山坑裡面才有這個 (註︰沒有原字幕)
They can only be found in small streams.
# 你看 這下面肯定有 那麼大的石頭
Look! There must be crabs under this rock.It's huge!
# 搬不動它
But I can't lift it.
# 你看 兄弟家 我去他家坐一坐
Look! My buddy lives there. I'm gonna have a cup of tea.
# 你看 兄弟家 大門緊閉
Look! My buddy's house. The door is tightly closed.
# 他還搞了一個鎖頭鎖著他家廚房
He has even put a lock there to lock up his kitchen.
# 回去
Let's go!
# 這個是昨天抓的螃蟹 今天帶它去
These are the crabs that we caught yesterday. Today, we're taking them,
# 河邊 把它烤啦
to the riverside. We'll grill them there.
# 就這裡了
Here is good.
# 剛好這裡有個小島
The small island here is just right.
# 好這裡 我去檢點柴火來
Let's get started here. I'm gonna pick some firewood,
# 把火生起來
and set the fire.
# 把這個柴先 搞斷它
This branch, let me chop it up first.
# 要裝點水哦
I need to get some water.
# 裝點水燒點 燒點開水燙一下那個螃蟹
I get some water and boil, boil some water and then blanch the crabs for a while.
# 夠了 一點點就夠了 不要那麼多
Enough. A tiny little bit is enough. I don't need that much.
# 哎呀 三個串 下去
Aya! Three in a row, get down!
# 一鍋煮啦
Blanch them all together.
# 先燙一下 不是煮
I just boil them for a while first, I'm not cooking them.
# 先燙一下 把它
I boil them for a while, so that,
# 燙S它來 (註︰我不想用"kill it"之類的字，怕惹來聖母婊，容我稍作修飾)
they don't move anymore.
# 還會動哦
They're still moving.
# 等它水開啦 就可以了
I only need to wait till the water boils.
# 你看 它們都紅了
Look! They've all become red.
# 再等一下
A few more moments
# 等它水沸騰了 我們就把它取出來
We're gonna take them out when the water boils.
# 好啦 差不多啦
Alright! It's almost there.
# 煮了好燙的水啊
The water is burning hot.
# 把水倒掉
I pour the water away.
# 裝點那裡的冷水來
Let me get some cold water there,
# 先給它泡
and soak them.
# 蟹黃都出來了
The glans are already leaking out.
# 金黃色的哦
It's golden yellow, you know.
# 要把這個蓋子裡面
I need to remove the guts,
# 內臟要把它去一下
inside the shell.
# 這個 這些都不能吃的
This, these are inedible.
# 好啦
Alright!
# 這些洗乾淨之後我們把蓋子蓋上去
We'll put the shells back to cover them after they're washed and cleaned.
# 然後就直接這樣烤
And then they can be grilled right away.
# 烤螃蟹
Grilled crabs
# 可以
Alright!
# 你看 又搞一個
Look! One more is done.
# 一二三四五六七八
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight,
# 九
nine
# 最後一個了
This is the last one.
# 螃蟹
Crabs
# 先把它們一個一個擺好
I first put them nicely and tidily one by one.
# 大的在中間
The big ones are in the middle,
# 小的在旁邊
while the small ones are on the sides.
# 這樣子剛剛好
They're well fitted on the net.
# 這個瞉一個個把它蓋上去
I put the shells back one by one.
# 應該是這樣子烤吧
I think I'm grilling in the right way.
# 可以了
It's fine now.
# 好啦
Alright!
# 先給它們洗一下
Let me wash them first.
# 晾在這裡先
Leave them here first.
# 我搞點醬料來
I'm gonna make some sauce.
# 多下點薑下去
Put more ginger.
# 夠了
Enough,
# 薑夠了
enough ginger
# 再加點這個鹽
Then some, some salt.
# 加點鹽
Put some salt.
# 加點料酒
Put some cooking wine.
# 加點醬油
Put some soy sauce.
# 加點油
Put some oil
# 搞點 辣椒醬
Get some, chilli sauce!
# 再搞點大蒜
And put some garlic as well.
# 攪拌一下
Shake them well.
# 搞點醬汁 搞點大蒜
Put some sauce, and some garlic.
# 反過來烤
Grill them upside down.
# 你看 這樣可以
Look! It's alright now!
# 先中間
In the middle first...
# 粘一點這個
Dip it into the, you know...
# 你看 這樣就很靚了
Look! It's really beautiful now!
# 它的 在它蓋子上蓋點
Its, on it's shell, I put some,
# 蓋點醬油 蓋點這個
put some sauce, and some, you know,
# 然後再沾一點這個料
and then dip into the ingredients.
# 啊 它味道
Ah! The taste is,
# 通通都給反過來
absolutely okay!
# 你看 把它們的頭對頭 尾對尾
I turn them all upside down.
# 鉗子對鉗子
Look! They're now head to head, tail to tail,
# 剛剛好
pincer to pincer.
# 烤 上烤架
Perfect!
# 你看 噴點油
Yea! Onto the grill!
# 你看
Look! I spray some oil.
# 這都
Look!
# 直接開啦
They're all,
# 瞉
already opened.
# 掀掉了
The shell,
# 不掀掉烤不熟
have already been taken off.
# 現在熟啦
Otherwise it would take forever to grill them.
# 嘗一下
Now it's done.
# 要從鉗子
Let me try,
# 燙
starting from, the pincer.
# 先要從鉗子開刀
Hot!
# 嗯 熟啦
I'll start from its pincer.
# 嗯 很鮮哦 這個
Um! It's done!
# 螃蟹就是螃蟹
Um! It's so fresh and tasty.
# 怪不得那麼多人喜歡吹
Crabs mean crabs.
# 就是有那種
No wonder it is a favourite food of so many people.
# 那種鮮味
It's because of the,
# 這全部腳
the taste of freshness and savory.
# 我們這邊的螃蟹 腳吃不了的
These are all legs.
# 只能吃它的肉
The legs of the crabs here are inedible.
# 肉又沒多少
Only the meat is edible.
# 只有鉗子好吃
But there's not so much meat.
# 你看 這個鉗子 鉗子的肉
Only the pincers are tasty.
# 嗯
Look! This is a pincer, meat in a pincer.
# 一點點
Um!
# 嗯 就是一種味 很鮮 很鮮美
A tiny little bit
# 這裡面還有一點點肉
Um! It's the taste of, freshness, and savory.
# 好啦 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
There's still a tiny little bit of meat inside.
# 把那火滅一下
Alright! The video ends here.
# Let's put off the fire.